<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Matt Makai</title><link href="http://www.mattmakai.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.mattmakai.com/feeds/future-post.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.mattmakai.com/</id><updated>2012-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Getting to Plan B</title><link href="http://www.mattmakai.com/getting-to-plan-b.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Matt Makai</name></author><id>tag:www.mattmakai.com,2012-12-27:getting-to-plan-b.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004OC07HQ/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=minimneeds-20&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B004OC07HQ"&gt;Getting to Plan B&lt;/a&gt;
by John Mullins and Randy Komisar is a book about transitioning from an
initial idea into a subsequent idea with a better product/market fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book introduces several key terms, including &lt;em&gt;analogs&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;antilogs&lt;/em&gt;,
&lt;em&gt;leaps of faith&lt;/em&gt;. The use of &lt;em&gt;dashboards&lt;/em&gt; is also a key concept and many
examples throughout the book are used to demonstrate their value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analogs are examples of companies, in the same industry you seek to do
business or a different industry, that have key similarities between how
they do business and your prospective business model. Antilogs are the
opposite - what you do not want to replicate. The mixture of analogs and
antilogs helps to define your business model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analogs and antilogs are intended to produce a basic level of evidence
that the way you plan to execute your business has already been proven by
other currently operating businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aspects of a business that are not &amp;quot;proven&amp;quot; by analogs and antilogs are
leaps of faith. Leaps of faith are hypotheses that must be proven if the
business is to work properly. Dashboards are used to constantly monitor
the leaps of faith. Leaps of faith change from high-level to granular
through multiple iterations of dashboarding and modifying the business
based on the results achieved (or not achieved).&lt;/p&gt;
</summary></entry></feed>